{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "The Sicilian Vespers helped prevent one of these events from occurring by burning the ships of Charles of Anjou in Messina harbor. The use of Greek Fire in the Bosphorus strait helped stop one of these events. A successful one of these events saw Orban design the massive Dardanelles cannon at the behest of Mehmed II. One of the most well known of these events was ordered by Enrico Dandolo during the Fourth Crusade. For ten points, name these events that involve looting the capitol of the Byzantine Empire.",
      "answer": "sacks of Constantinople"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man claimed to use a hand-pumped rail car to scout for trains while on an unapproved mission in Veracruz. This general neutralized Raubal in his direction of Operation Cartwheel, a year after an invasion on the Lingayen Gulf forced his retreat to Corregidor. Six months after the Wake Island Conference, this man was dismissed from command of a war in which he organized the Inchon landing. For ten points, name this commander of U.N. forces during the Korean War, who proclaimed “I shall return” to the Philippines during World War II.",
      "answer": "Douglas MacArthur"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1996, “Bob Dole” and “Clinton” were used interchangeably in one of these documents. One of these documents referenced Dieppe the day before it was raided, and these documents accidentally used codenames learned from American soldiers in the leadup to D-Day. For aesthetic purposes, these documents usually feature radial symmetry and no “cheater” black squares.” for ten points, name these word games, edited by Will Shortz for the New York Times, which feature clues to fill in words going across and down.",
      "answer": "crossword puzzles"
    },
    {
      "question": "Alfred Blunt, Bishop of Bradford, delivered an address against this event and advocated “divine grace” for its subject. A missed meeting at the Aberdeen Royal Infirmary helped fan suspicion about this event. Walter Monckton assisted with the legal issues of this event, and Stanley Baldwin blocked an attempt by this event’s perpetrator to address the nation. Socialite Wallis Simpson provoked, for ten points, what 1936 event, the only formal renunciation of the throne since the Anglo-Saxon period?",
      "answer": [
        "abdication of Edward VIII",
        "synonyms for “abdicate,” such as Edward VIII giving up the British throne before “formal” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The ruling in this case overruled an appelate ruling that found that the “Constitution is silent on the subject,” thereby protecting the implied power of Congress to carry out constitutional laws by “necessary and proper” means. Chief Justice John Marshall noted that “the power to tax involves the power to destroy” in his unanimous decision in, for ten points, what 1819 Supreme Court case lodged against the Bank of the United States by the state of Maryland?",
      "answer": "McCulloch v. Maryland"
    },
    {
      "question": "This empire won a battle by using hit-and-run tactics, then feigning retreat to lure Kitbuqa’s army into a trap; in that battle, this empire was led by Baibars and Saif ad-Din Qutuz. Shortly after Hulagu sacked Aleppo, this empire won the aforementioned Battle of Ain Jalut and retook Syria from the Mongols. These people created a sultanate centered in Cairo after ending the Ayyubid Dynasty. For ten points, name this class of Islamic soldiers in Egypt that originated from Turkish slaves.",
      "answer": "Mamluk sultanate"
    },
    {
      "question": "The subject of this film was inspired by its star’s study with Roger Revelle. Oklahoma Senator Jim Inhofe compared this film to Hitler’s Mein Kampf. This film won Best Original Song for Melissa Etheridge’s“INeedtoWakeUp,”anditexplainstheKeelingCurveina“slideshow”thatshowsretreating glaciers and other damage caused by the greenhouse effect. For ten points, name this 2006 documentary in which former Vice President Al Gore gives a presentation on the dangers of global warming.",
      "answer": "An Inconvenient Truth"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Mongols supposedly filled nine sacks with these objects after defeating Henry the Pious of Silesia at Legnica. During the Vietnam War, 101st Airborne’s Tiger Force unit was accused of creating necklaces out of these objects. James Oglethorpe led troops at the battles of Gully Hole Creek and Bloody Marsh in a war named for one of these objects lost by a smuggler; after three years, that war became a part of the larger War of the Austrian Succession. Robert Jenkins lost, for ten points, what body part?",
      "answer": [
        "severed ears",
        "War of Jenkins’ Ear"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s concept of “election” was rejected by Karl Barth. The Consensus Tigurinus resolved a dispute between this man and Huldrych Zwingli [z’ving-lee] over the nature of the Eucharist. Nicolas de la Fontaine brought Michael Servetus to trial on behalf of this man, which led to Servetus being burned at the stake. He believed that God alone chooses who is saved, according to his idea of predestination. For ten points, name this French Protestant and author of The Institutes of Christian Religion who led the Reformation in Geneva.",
      "answer": "John Calvin"
    },
    {
      "question": "During the writing of the Articles of Confederation, New Hampshire and New York blocked the adoption of this measure. Roger Sherman and James Wilson re-introduced this measure at the Constitutional Convention, preserving language about the exclusion of “Indians not taxed.” The Thirteenth Amendment nullified this clause of the Constitution, which was used to balance Congressional representation between the North and South. For ten points, name this compromise regarding the value of the American slave population, which used a fractional formula.",
      "answer": "Three-Fifths Compromise"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this event, a comparison to David and Jonathan was used to answer the question “What is the ‘love that dare not speak its name?’” This event was triggered by the Marquess of Queensbury’s victory in a libel suit. In its aftermath, its subject wrote a 50,000 word letter to “Bosie” while serving a sentence of hard labor at Reading Gaol [redding jail]. For ten points, name this 1895 event in which the author of The Picture of Dorian Gray and The Importance of Being Earnest was convicted of inappropriate relations with Lord Alfred Douglas.",
        "answer": [
          "the trial of Oscar Wilde for homosexuality or Regina v. Wilde",
          "descriptions of Oscar Wilde being arrested and/or charged for homosexual behavior, gross indecency and/or sodomy",
          "imprisonment of Oscar Wilde"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Wilde’s 50,000 word letter was given this title, from the Latin for “from the depths.”",
        "answer": "De Profundis"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One leader of this organization sued William Havemeyer for libel; Havemeyer died on the day of that trial. This organization, led by “Honest” John Kelly, faded away shortly after the fall of Carmine DiSapio. The first Catholic nominee for president, Al Smith, was strongly backed by this organization, which was developed by Aaron Burr but lost influence during Franklin D. Roosevelt’s governorship. Thomas Nast depicted this group as a tiger devouring democracy in 1871. Boss Tweed led, for ten points, what New York political machine?",
        "answer": [
          "Tammany Hall",
          "Society of St. Tammany",
          "Sons of St. Tammany"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In spite of Tammany Hall opposition, this Italian-American was elected mayor of New York in 1933 and served for 12 years.",
        "answer": "Fiorello H. La Guardia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ethnic group was the primary target of the Hamidian massacres and is the subject of The Memoirs of Naim Bey. Operation Nemesis was carried out by members of this ethnic group, who were targeted by Red Sunday and the Tehcir Law. Mass killings of these people were carried out by the Committee of Union and Progress, led by the Three Pashas. For ten points, name this ethnic group, the victims of a 1915 genocide perpetrated by the Ottomans that Turkey still denies today.",
        "answer": "Armenians"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After the end of World War I, numerous Ottoman officials were exiled to this modern day country. This Mediterranean island earned a collective George Cross in 1942 for World War II bravery.",
        "answer": "Malta"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One member of this team was suspended six games for headbutting referee Ted Bernhardt, then another 11 games a year later for kicking a cameraman in the groin. Other players for this team included Toni Kukoc [koo-”coach”] and Luc Longley. During President Obama’s 2016 visit with the champion Warriors, he noted that one member of this team, the “greatest of all time,” was with them: coach Steve Kerr. For ten points, name this NBA team that won 72 games in 1995-96, the first year of the second “three-peat” of championships won by Phil Jackson, Scottie Pippen, and Michael Jordan.",
        "answer": [
          "Chicago Bulls",
          "either"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Hall of Fame rebounder earned the aforementioned suspensions, in addition to three rings with the Bulls. He has earned criticism for his recent “hoops diplomacy” efforts in Asia.",
        "answer": "Dennis Rodman"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Pintupi Nine were a group of these people, another group of which helped John King survive the Burke and Willis expedition. The Pilbara strike was led by these people, whose land rights were recognized in the Mabo case, which overturned the decision made in the Gove lands rights case. This group “scarred” trees for their bark to create coolamons. In 2008, Kevin Rudd apologized to these people for his country’s government removing their children from their care. For ten points, name these original inhabitants of Australia.",
        "answer": [
          "Australian Aborigines",
          "equivalents like indigenous people of Australia"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This term refers to the children taken from Aboriginal families and raised by white foster families in the 20th century.",
        "answer": "Stolen Generation or stolen children"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This composer’s second symphony was dedicated to George Butterworth, who was later killed in World War I, and includes the Westminster Chimes in its finale. He depicted the doomed expedition of Robert Scott to the South Pole in his seventh symphony. This composer of A London Symphony and Sinfonia antarctica used a violin to depict the title bird in another piece. For ten points, name this British composer of The Lark Ascending and Fantasia on “Greensleeves”.",
        "answer": "Ralph Vaughan Williams"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Ralph Vaughan Williams also wrote a Fantasia on a theme of this 16th century Baroque English composer, who composed for Queen Elizabeth I and is best known for a forty-voice motet, Spem in alium.",
        "answer": "Thomas Tallis"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "James Farmer coined the name for these people, who John Siegenthaler was trying to assist when he was knocked unconscious with a pipe. The lack of enforcement of the Supreme Court’s decision in Boynton v. Virginia inspired these people, as that case was supposed to prevent discrimination in public transportation. The Congress of Racial Equality, or CORE, was one sponsor of the Journey of Reconciliation taken by these people, who were firebombed and chased by white mobs. For ten points, give this term for civil rights activists who took buses into the segregated South in the 1960s.",
        "answer": "Freedom Riders"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This civil rights organization, co-founded by Julian Bond and chaired by John Lewis, sent students to assist with the Freedom Rides. It dropped “non-violent” from its name during Stokely Carmichael’s leadership of this group.",
        "answer": [
          "Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee or SNCC",
          "Student National Coordinating Committee"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man, who tried Archbishop Aloysius Stepinac for collaborating with the Nazis, led the only Eastern European nation that accepted aid from the ECA. He defeated Chetnik leader Draa Mihailovic [mee-hail-oh-vitch] before reaching his highest office. This man’s country was kicked out of COMINFORM after his feud with Stalin led to a break with the USSR in 1949. For ten points, name this communist ruler of Yugoslavia and guerrilla leader during World War II.",
        "answer": "Josip Broz Tito"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Tito was the first Secretary General of this group, which Sukarno and Kwame Nkrumah helped found in 1961.",
        "answer": "Non-Aligned Movement or NAM"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Native Americans",
      "prompt": "Which Native American tribe or ethnic group...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Inspired the name of the capital of Wyoming?",
          "answer": "Cheyenne"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was scouted for “code talkers” like Chester Nez during World War II?",
          "answer": "Navajo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is divided into Santee, Yankton, and Lakota groups?",
          "answer": "Sioux"
        },
        {
          "question": "Had a syllabary invented by Sequoyah?",
          "answer": "Cherokee"
        },
        {
          "question": "Fought three wars in Florida, the first two against Andrew Jackson?",
          "answer": "Seminole"
        },
        {
          "question": "Includes groups like the Zuni and Hopi and was named by the Spanish for the adobe buildings they lived in?",
          "answer": "Pueblo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Gave its name to a downslope wind common off the Rockies in the Great Plains, which can cause rapid temperature changes?",
          "answer": "Chinook"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the easternmost member of the Five Nations and was led by Joseph Brant?",
          "answer": "Mohawk"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Middle Ages English Rulers",
      "prompt": "Who...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Died at Bosworth Field and was the third and last English king of his name?",
          "answer": "Richard III"
        },
        {
          "question": "Signed the Magna Carta in 1215?",
          "answer": "John Lackland or John Softsword"
        },
        {
          "question": "Clashed with Guthrum and was the only English king called “the Great”?",
          "answer": "Alfred the Great"
        },
        {
          "question": "Defeated the Scots at Falkirk and was nicknamed for his height?",
          "answer": [
            "Edward Longshanks",
            "Edward I"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Ordered the St. Brices Day Massacre and was nicknamed for his ill-counsel?",
          "answer": [
            "Aethelred the Unready",
            "Aethelred II"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Signed the Provisions of Oxford and clashed with Simon de Montfort?",
          "answer": "Henry III"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was born Nicholas Breakspear and became the only English Pope?",
          "answer": "Adrian IV"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ascended to the throne following the Anarchy and Treaty of Wallingford?",
          "answer": "Henry II"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "A War Within a War",
      "prompt": "Which conflict...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Included bombing of the Ho Chi Minh trail as part of the larger Cold War?",
          "answer": "Vietnam War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was in part triggered by the smaller Bear Flag Revolt in California?",
          "answer": "Mexican-American War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Included British troops fighting in Spain as part of the Napoleonic Wars?",
          "answer": "Peninsular War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was named for the lack of fighting on the Western Front during the early stages of World War 2?",
          "answer": "Phoney War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Included the smaller Tanker War and the use of chemical weapons at Halabja?",
          "answer": "Iran-Iraq War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the North American theater of the War of Spanish Succession and was named for a monarch?",
          "answer": "Queen Anne’s War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was a revolt against Mazarin and Louis XIV during the Franco-Spanish War?",
          "answer": "the Fronde"
        },
        {
          "question": "Included smaller wars such as the Hannibal War and War of Mantuan Succession?",
          "answer": "Thirty Year’s War"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This party negotiated with Adolph Joffe for aid on the condition that this party allied itself with a rival; that alliance ended in the April 12th incident. The confiscation of contraband cigarettes from a 40 year old widow sparked the 2-28 (20 pts)",
        "massacre carried out by this party. In January 2016, this party lost a presidential election to the Democratic Progressive Party’s candidate Tsai Ing-Wen. This party was founded shortly after the (10 pts)",
        "Xinhai Revolution by Song Jiaoren and Sun Yat-Sen. For ten points, name this Taiwanese political party, founded in 1911 in China by Chiang Kai-Shek."
      ],
      "answer": "Kuomintang or KMT"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Wisconsin’s Supreme Court was the only state supreme court to declare one of these laws unconstitutional, although that decision was overturned in the case of Ableman v. Booth. Pierce Butler and Charles Pinckney proposed the clause in the (20 pts)",
        "Constitution that led to the development of the first of these laws in 1793. “Personal liberty laws” were meant to circumvent these laws, which were invalidated by the (10 pts)",
        "13th Amendment. For ten points, identify these laws, one of which was also passed in 1850, which stated that certain property could be returned to its owners after escape into a free state."
      ],
      "answer": "Fugitive Slave Laws"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This scientist’s Ostomachion is a tangram-like puzzle with 14 pieces. His geometric accomplishments include relating the volumes of a cylinder and sphere with equal radius and using a method of exhaustion to estimate 22/7 as an upper bound for (20 pts)",
        "pi. His military inventions include a mechanical claw to lift ships out of the water and a (10 pts)",
        "“death ray” designed using parabolic mirrors to try to burn incoming ships, meant to protect his home city during the Punic wars. A device that lifts liquids through rotation is a screw named for, for ten points, what Syracuse mathematician?"
      ],
      "answer": "Archimedes"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One work that studies this process describes how the oloa and tonga were brought together after a childbirth in Samoa. Delayed reciprocity is often a feature of this process, which is performed in the kula ring and (20 pts)",
        "potlatch ceremonies in Melanesia and the Pacific Northwest, respectively. Marcel Mauss’s 1925 magnum opus describes this process, which does not come with the guarantee of future (10 pts)",
        "rewards. Anthropologists have intensely studied, for ten points, what mode of exchange, contrasted with bartering?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "gift exchange",
        "descriptions and equivalents, like gift giving"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After one victory, this ruler’s forces caught the enemy horka, Bulcsu, and executed him. This ruler requested his son to be married to a Byzantine princess, Theophanu. This ruler had Pope Leo VIII elected after his predecessor entered negotiations with the son of Berengar II. Liudolf of (20 pts)",
        "Swabia led a revolt against this ruler after his marriage to Adelaide of Italy. This son of Henry the Fowler was crowned by (10 pts)",
        "Pope John XII seven years after his forces defeated the Magyars at the Battle of Lechfeld. For ten points, name this first Germanic Holy Roman Emperor."
      ],
      "answer": "Otto I, Holy Roman Emperor"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Two answers required. These two universities co-founded edX, an online education platform, in 2012. Dr. Eric Lander, who published a controversial revisionist history of the development of CRISPR [”crisper”] DNA segments in January 2015, directs the (20 pts)",
        "Broad Institute, a collaboration between these two schools. These schools also collaborate in a Masters’ program between one’s Sloan School of Management and the other’s (10 pts)",
        "Kennedy School of Government. For ten points, name these two universities, both located on the north side of the Charles River in Cambridge, Massachusetts."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Harvard University and Massachusetts Institute of Technology or MIT",
        "in either order",
        "prompt if only one is given"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man wrote that “The ‘power to regulate commerce among the several States’ cannot include a power to construct roads and canals” in his veto of the Bonus Bill. Macon’s (20 pts)",
        "Bills were passed under this President, repealing the Non-Intercourse Act. The charter for the first Bank of the United States expired under this man; five years later, he launched the (10 pts)",
        "Second Bank of the United States to help finance the rebuilding efforts after the War of 1812. For ten points, name this founding father who preceded James Monroe as U.S. President."
      ],
      "answer": "James Madison"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A 28-volume work on this subject opened with the call to sell your townhouse and give up the household gods of the city; that work was written in Punic by Mago. In another work, the author teaches this subject to his squanderous brother (20 pts)",
        "Perses. The “works” of Hesiod’s Works and Days details how to be successful at this practice, which Cincinnatus (10 pts)",
        "resumed after his dictatorships. For ten points, name this practice which includes animal husbandry, beekeeping, and the cultivation of crops for food."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "agriculture",
        "farming",
        "equivalents",
        "any specific form, such as beekeeping",
        "making wine"
      ]
    }
  ]
}